Guide to the James Hazen Hyde Papers 1874-1940, 1953 MS 319
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Diaries, 1922-1940; 12 Linear feet in 12 record cartons
  - Diary, 1933 April-May (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1933 June-August (Box 25, Folder 4)
    On August 17, Hyde dines with [Joseph] Duveen, among others, and recounts an anecdote told by Duveen of why he bought a picture at a Christie's auction from the Lord Baltimore collection at a price higher than its value.
  - Diary, 1933 September-October (Box 25, Folder 5)
    On September 30, Hyde and his wife ("Tommie") travel on the Orient Express, arriving in Austria, especially Vienna. They are there for the rest of the diary. Among other activities (mostly cultural), they visit various churches and other cultural institutions, often with art historian Hans Tietze. Among the programs in the diary from this trip are those from the Wiener Philharmoniker (featuring Arturo Toscanini) and from the Burgtheater (featuring Richard Beer-Hofmann's Faust).
  - Diary, 1933 November-December (Box 25, Folder 6)
    The Hydes's trip to Austria continues. On November 22, they travel to Berlin. They return to Paris on December 9. Hyde takes his son, Henry, now age 18, to the American Consulate to formalize Henry's intention to declare himself an American citizen.
  - Diary, 1934 January (Box 25, Folder 7)
    On January 22, Hyde's son is in a car accident in England, but survives. Hyde meets with Sato, the Japanese ambassador to France.
  - Diary, 1934 February (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Diary, 1934 March (with original binder) (Box 25, Folder 9)
    The diary opens with a "memorandum" concerning the convention of 1932 between the U.S. and France on double taxation; the memo is dated "Paris, February 26, 1934" but its authorship is unattributed. The memo is in English, with a shorter French version. On March 3, Hyde visits Finance Minister Germain Martin at the request of American ambassador Straus; he summarizes the separate exchanges he had with Straus and Martin. On March 29, Hyde goes to Berlin with Helfer and Frank.
  - Diary, 1934 April-May (Box 26, Folder 1)
    The Hydes's trip to Germany continues, through April 23, when they travel on to Czechoslovakia and Prague. On April 29, Hyde meets with President Masaryk. Leaves Czechoslovakia on May 19 for Poland (Cracow/Krakow and Warsaw). Left for Berlin on May 31 at the diary's close.
  - Diary, 1934 June-August (Box 26, Folder 2)
    The diary opens in Berlin, but the trip ends on June 7.
  - Diary, 1934 September-October (Box 26, Folder 3)
    The Hydes begin a trip to London on October 29.
  - Diary, 1934 November-December (2 folders) (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
    The Hydes trip to London continues until December 7.
  - Diary, 1935 January-February (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Diary, 1935 March-April (Box 26, Folder 7)
    Hyde travels to Berlin on March 11, meeting and traveling with Hensler for part of the time there. He traveled on to Budapest on April 8 and Vienna on April 20.
  - Diary, 1935 May-June (with original binder) (Box 26, Folder 8)
    Hyde's visit to Austria continues; his wife, Tommie, joins him from Paris on May 6. Handwritten documents, in German, from conductor Carl von Alwin at May 12 and June 4. Includes an extended summary of Hyde's conversation over supper with Ambassador Messersmith on May 24. On May 30, Hyde travels with Tietze to Linz and the surrounding area; along the way presumably Tietze (the name is cut out of the diary) tells Hyde of the increasing police power in Austria; later travels with Tommie in Salzburg and other parts of Austria. Arrives in Munich on June 13, then returning to Paris on June 17.
  - Diary, 1935 July-August (Box 27, Folder 1)
    On August 18, Hyde receives notice that the German art historian Erwin Hensler died; Hensler appears frequently in Hyde's entries during his trips to Germany and here Hyde reflects on Hensler.
  - Diary, 1935 September (Box 27, Folder 2)
    On September 16, Hyde meets with General Charles Sherrill, who had met with Hitler as arranged by the German ambassador Koster (see September 17). Sherrill voiced optimism about Germany, noting everyone seemed prosperous under Hitler's regime. Hyde disagrees, but appreciates "the propaganda value of dictators."
  - Diary, 1935 September-November (Box 27, Folder 3)
    The diary opens on September 27, with Hyde traveling to Munich, where he visits Dr. Berliner, among others. On October 5, he goes on to Vienna, where he remains, traveling in the area, for the balance of the diary.
  - Diary, 1935 December, 1935-1936 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    Hyde leaves Vienna on December 3 for Berlin (Tommie joins him there on December 12), where he remains for the balance of the diary. On December 21, Hyde is given a tour by Otto Meyer of the stadium and other buildings for the upcoming Olympics.Whether out of discretion or other reason, Hyde's entries for this trip seem to avoid almost all topics but cultural matters.
  - Diary, 1936 January (Box 27, Folder 5)
    The Hydes's trip to Berlin continues. A typescript of a letter to Hyde from Ambassador William Dodd is included at January 7, conveying a sense of potential danger to Germans who accept invitations from Dodd. On January 16, sees more of the Olympics facilities with Otto Meyer.
  - Diary, 1936 February (Box 27, Folder 6)
    The Hydes continue in Germany. Attends the "Horse Show" (VII. Internationales Reit-Und Fahrturnier); the program is in the diary. On February 6, visits the Harnack Haus (illustrated booklet included in diary). On February 7, is given a tour of Dahlem by Dr. von Cranach, who points out the building in which poison gas was invented; Hyde observes Cranach smiling as he said it. The Hydes left Berlin for Paris on February 25. At the back of the diary is a draft and corrected draft of a document "Impressions de Voyage," in French and presumably written by Hyde upon his departure from Germany.
  - Diary, 1936 March-April (Box 27, Folder 7)
    Diary includes the last day of February and May 1 in addition to the core March-April pages. Includes the checklist for the 1936 annual exhibition of the Cercle de l'Union Artistique. On March 11, Hyde met with Ambassador Straus and "left him some notes," possibly those found in the February 1936 diary. At page 93 are two original letters from Arthur Popham Pope, one to Hyde and the other to Mrs. Hyde, commenting at length on the European situation.
  - Diary, 1936 May (Box 27, Folder 8)
    Met with friend who had returned from Italy and was enthusiastic about its state after meeting with Mussolini.
  - Diary, 1936 June-July (Box 27, Folder 9)
    On June 4, Hyde takes the Orient Express to Vienna. On June 26 he goes to Semmering, Austria, for a few days before returning to Paris on July 3. At page 90, there is typescript of a letter from Louis Germain Martin (in French).
  - Diary, 1936 August-September (Box 27, Folder 10)
    At page 81, includes a handwritten poem from the Alwyns to the Hydes; written on stationery of Pavillon de l'Ermitage at Versailles. On September 3, Hyde finds in old files lists of the directors of the various companies he was involved with in the United States (lists are in the diary at page 95); these include American Surety Company, Commercial Trust Company of Philadelphia, Equitable Life Assurance Society, Metropolitan Opera Company, New Theatre, and several others. There are several clippings, programs, etc. related to the celebration of Harvard's 300th anniversary.
  - Diary, 1936 October-November (Box 27, Folder 11)
    The Hydes travel to Vienna on October 1 where they remain throughout this diary.
  - Diary, 1936 December-1937 January (1 of 2 folders), 1936-1937 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    The Hydes continue in Vienna. Stayed until December 21, when they left for Munich.
  - Diary, 1936 December-1937 January (1 of 2 folders), 1936-1937 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    On January 1, the Hydes leave Munich for Berlin where they stay for this diary.
  - Diary, 1937 February-March (Box 28, Folder 2)
    Visit in Berlin continues. On February 8, Hyde met General Goering at a dinner at the French Embassy. Tommie left for Paris on February 14, but Hyde remained behind. On February 28, Hyde attends the Opera Ball, which Goering also attends. Hyde returns to Paris on March 4.
  - Diary, 1937 April-May (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1937 June-July (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1937 August-October (with original binder) (Box 28, Volume 1)
    The diary opens with the Hydes apparently attending the dedication of the American Meuse-Argonne War Memorial (program included), then traveling to Austria and Germany, starting in Salzburg and Munich; returns to Paris on August 24. (This diary begins a new form of binder for the documents, which was used for the balance of the volumes; the first three original binders were retained as examples, with the remainder removed to folders.)
  - Diary, 1937 November-December (with original binder) (Box 28, Volume 2)
    On November 1, Hyde travels to Munich with Helfer, Perrot and Frank, then on to Vienna on November 4; Tommie joins Hyde on December 6.
  - Diary, 1938 January-February (with original binder) (Box 28, Volume 3)
    Visit to Vienna continues until February 1 when the Hydes go to Berlin.
  - Diary, 1938 March-April (2 folders) (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
    Hyde and his wife, Tommie's, travels in Germany continue. Goes to the Reichstag on March 19 to hear Hitler and Goering. Tommie returns to Paris in late March while Hyde goes on to London where he makes his typical rounds of embassies, social engagements, and cultural events, including going with Raymond Recouly to see "Nine Sharp" at the Little Theatre, among several others (programs included). On April 1, he attends a lunch given by the Foreign Press Association at which Viscount Halifax provides two anecdotes by way of illustrating the "English character." Tommie rejoins him in London in mid-April. The diary includes a picture postcard postmarked (with swastikas) from Austria featuring a drawing of Hitler. Hyde has meetings with Count Colleredo-Mansfield whose life in Austria has been ruined by the Nazis but is uncertain whether to return there or not.
  - Diary, 1938 May-July (Box 29, Folder 3)
    The Hydes continue in London. On May 10, attends a gala perfomance of the ballet at the Sadler's Wells Theatre, given in the Queen's presence (program included). The Hydes return to Paris on May 18. On May 20, Hyde meets with architect Patrice Bonnet who seeks to build a musical center at Versailles; Hyde provides counsel as to the geopolitical implications of his plans. The King and Queen of England visit France on July 22 and Hyde describes some of the related events; the diary includes a related program and an identification card with photograph of Hyde.
  - Diary, 1938 August-November (2 folders) (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
    In August, Hyde stayed at Aix-les-Bains for health reasons. On August 9, Hyde has lunch with a Reverend Pere Gillet who describes the Pope's anger with the pro-Nazi attitude of Austrian cardinal Innitzer, who explains it as related to Hitler's promise of special treatment to Austrian and German Catholics. On August 19, he meets with French ambassador to the U.S. Comte de Saint-Quentin and Hyde documents various anecdotes he hears related to American-German relations. Hyde's sister dies and he attends her funeral in Paris at the American Cathedral on September 9. On September 16 sees the film "Jeunesse Olympique" and bemoans the contrast between nations working together on sports, but not in other realms. On September 30, Hyde meets with Hugo Burghauser who explains he escaped from Austria with only his musical instruments and clothes, and is headed for New York. As the Czechoslovakia situation intensifies, France begins to mobilize for war; workers appear at Hyde's home in Versailles to plan defensive trenches. On October 23, has lunch with Hans Tietze and his wife who left Austria just before the Anschluss and are also heading for the U.S.
  - Diary, 1938 December-1939 February (2 folders), 1938-1939 (Box 29, Folder 6-7)
    The Hydes go to Cannes and the French Riviera in January. Visit Tardieu's new home at Menton on February 2 and provide description of it; the menu of their lunch is included.
  - Diary, 1939 March-April (2 folders) (Box 29, Folder 8-9)
    Hyde travels to the Netherlands(the Hague, Amsterdam, Leeuwarden, etc.) beginning in mid-April, motors with Sarah Benton, visits bookdealers, antiquarians, and museums. On April 27, Hyde rides a diesel-electric train of the Netherlands Railways; diary includes itinerary, train description, and 3 photographs.
  - Diary, 1939 May-June (2 folders) (Box 29, Folder 10-11)
    Hyde's trip to the Netherlands continues until about May 6, primarily visiting art museums.
  - Diary, 1939 July-August (2 folders) (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
    On July 4, a newspaper article about an 1874 kidnap victim, Charley Ross, causes Hyde to recall that the event had created fear at the time in Hyde's father and "poisoned" Hyde's youth. On July 6, attends and describes Sacha Guitry's fourth wedding (invitation in diary). On July 13, meets with Pierre Verlet of the Louvre, who will be cataloging Hyde's collection on the four parts of the world. July 19 includes a transcription of a letter and related obituary Hyde received from Naomi DesVernay regarding the death of her husband, William, an African-American who apparently worked for Hyde around 1900 and had expressed admiration to his wife about Hyde. On July 28, the Hydes travel to Geneva and elsewhere in Switzerland. On July 30 visits the Palais de la Societe des Nations and comments positively on the building. Had meetings with archaeologist Arthur Evans who was staying in the same hotel. On August 3, Hyde documents his visit with Henry de Rothschild. Hyde returns to Paris on August 23, noting that the German-Russian treaty will "complicate the situation which is already bad enough." August 24 includes a notice from the American Embassy advising American citizens to return to the U.S. In the following days, members of Hyde's household staff are mobilized for war and leave.
  - Diary, 1939 September-November (2 folders) (Box 30, Folder 3A-B)
    France declares war on Germany and Hyde discusses the mobilization, his concerns about his exposure at his home in Versailles, his attempts to make himself useful as during World War I, and other matters related to the opening of the war, though he continues his walks, social rounds, lunches at the Ritz, visits to the cinema, etc. During this time, John Jay Ide is staying as a guest at Hyde's home in Versailles. On September 22 he meets with Lefeuvre, formerly of the French Embassy in Berlin, who described the departure of the staff from the embassy. On November 3, Hyde notes "War is a very fatiguing and depressing affair," which captures the general tone of many of his entries at this time.
  - Diary, 1939 December-1940 February (2 folders), 1939-1940 (Box 30, Folder 4-5)
    Traveled to Switzerland (Bern) beginning January 10, returning on February 3, expressing comfort with being back with the French Army and Maginot Line. On February 6, sees the film "Mr. Smith Goes to Washington," which he likes.
  - Diary, 1940 March-April (with original binder) (2 folders) (Box 30, Folder 6-7)
    March 21 includes a carbon copy of a letter from a Dean to E.B. Close of the American Hospital of Paris regarding the American Hospital's and the Red Cross's plans for relief in France. On March 28, sees the "Jewish propaganda film" Apres Mein Kampf les Crimes and provides an extended critique and impressions of key scenes. At page 168 is a carbon copy of a memo from Paul Azan of the Comite Militaire Franco-Finlandais titled "L'Action en Scandinavie"; numbered as 30 and dated March 15; the memo is updated by number 51 dated April 6, also here, and number 54 dated April 19 (at page 212). 10 sheets total, all in French. On April 11, Hyde meets with his lawyer, Robinson, to finish his new will. The diaries end at April 30, a few weeks before the German invasion of France.
- Series V. Cercle Francais and Other, Related Scrapbooks, 1894-1905; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons of bound volumes
  The series includes seven scrapbooks concerning the Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard, one concerning the Alliance Francaise, one that has documents concerning both organizations, and one that relates to the visit of Harvard professor Barrett Wendell to France in 1905. The Cercle scrapbooks range from Hyde's entry in the club in 1894 to the end of his active involvement with it upon his departure for France in 1905. The first five Cercle scrapbooks, through 1900, are especially rich with correspondence and other documents reflecting Hyde's deep involvement as an energetic officer of the club and as the financial source for the annual lecture series he instituted in 1898. After 1900, the Cercle scrapbooks are mostly clippings with some ephemera. Nonetheless, the Cercle scrapbooks provide rich documentation of the organization's activities for the years they cover, notably in the expansion of the Cercle under Hyde from a local club catering to its members to one having a national and international reputation and impact. In addition to documentation of the lecture series, including the national reach of the lectures, the scrapbooks document the annual plays performed by the Cercle. Later years include images of the casts in costume. The scrapbooks do not hold any official records of the Cercle, such as meeting minutes or financial reports.
  The one volume of material concerning the Alliance Francais includes mostly clippings for the years 1900-1903, but there is also informative program lists and other ephemera related to the Alliance's activities for the first few years of its existence. The Barrett Wendell scrapbook holds primarily clippings with some ephemera.
  All but the scrapbook concerning the Alliance Francaise were a gift of James Hazen Hyde in April 1947. The Alliance Francaise scrapbook was a gift from Hyde in October 1948, along with related correspondence (see Series III).
  - Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard Scrapbook (Vol. 1), 1894-1898 (Box 31)
    Includes, among other subjects, extensive documentation (correspondence, meeting transcript, legal opinions) concerning the 1897 conflict between the Cercle (i.e., Hyde) and Professor F.C. de Sumichrast, and Sumichrast's resignation as member and officer of the club. This event led to Hyde, then Vice-President, becoming President of the Cercle and the manner of his assertion of its independence of the Harvard French Department. Includes documents related to Hyde's creation of a $30,000 trust fund for lecturers, and the appearance of the first speaker, René Doumic, funded by the trust.
  - Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard Scrapbook (Vol. 2), 1898 (Box 31)
    Includes, among many other subjects, a November 15 letter from Adolphe Cohn to Hyde describing the founding and early years of the Cercle (1886-89). Includes documents related to Hyde's activism as president at attempting to expand the Cercle's reputation nationally and internationally; these include correspondence with Ferdinand W. Peck, the Commissioner-General for the United States to the Paris Exposition of 1900, requesting space for the Cercle Francais at the U.S. exhibit.
  - Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard Scrapbook (Vol. 3), 1899 (Box 31)
    Among many other subjects, Hyde's efforts to have the Cercle represented at the 1900 Paris Exposition draw in U.S. Senator Thomas Platt and gain ground. Includes documentation of Edouard Roy's visit to the U.S. (Roy was the second lecturer funded by Hyde), including photographs of Roy on board a transatlantic steamer and the steamer's arrival (or departure). References to the Alliance Francais begin to appear in this volume as do Hyde's efforts to encourage the creation of other Cercles at other universities, including University of Pennsylvania.
  - Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard Scrapbook (Vol. 4), 1899 (Box 31)
    Includes, among many other subjects, arrangements for the third lecturer funded by Hyde, Henri de Régnier. Hyde gets approval for the Cercle to be represented at the Paris Exposition; the scrapbook includes correspondence related to the arrangements.
  - Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard Scrapbook (Vol. 5), 1900 (Box 32)
    Among other subjects, extensive clippings concerning the visit of Henri de Régnier to the U.S. Includes the cover page of "The Underwriter" insurance trade journal, featuring a profile photo of Hyde in connection with his appointment to the Legion of Honor; also many related clippings.
  - Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard Scrapbook (Vol. 6), 1900-1901 (Box 32)
    Among other subjects, clippings related to the Cercle's medal-winning exhibit at the Paris Exposition, including an image of it from the press. Clippings related to Gaston Deschamps, the fourth lecturer funded by Hyde.
  - Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard Scrapbook (Vol. 7), 1901-1903 (Box 32)
    Among other subjects, clippings related to the fifth lecturer funded by Hyde, Hugues Le Roux. Later pages of the scrapbook also include clippings related to Hyde's activities with the Alliance Francaise.
  - Cercle Francais and Alliance Francaise Scrapbook, 1898-1905 (Box 32)
    Includes various documents related to the five lecturers selected and funded by Hyde in 1898-1902(René Doumic, Edouard Roy, Henri de Régnier, Gaston Deschamps, Hugues Le Roux), including itineraries, lecture topics, university contacts for lecture arrangements, publicity, and cabinet card photographs of Roy, Régnier and Deschamps. Includes similar documents for lectures arranged by Hyde under the auspices of the Federation de l'Alliance Francaise aux Etats-Unis in 1903-1905; lecturers represented are Leopold Mabilleau, André Michel, Anatole Leroy-Beaulieu, Vincent de Wierzbicki, Robert Dupouey, René Millet, and Frantz Funck-Brentano.
  - Alliance Francaise Scrapbook (Vol. 1), 1900-1903 (Box 32)
    Clippings, membership lists, constitution and by-laws, invitations, lists of programs, and other ephemera. The circumstances of Hyde's election as president in 1902 are described in some English language clippings. (The binder refers to this as Volume 1 for the Alliance Francaise, but there are no other such volumes in the collection.)
  - Barrett Wendell Scrapbook, 1905 (Box 31)
    Primarily clippings concerning the lectures in Paris of Harvard Professor Barrett Wendell. Also, an advertising piece for a performance of Barrett's play "Raleigh in Guiana." There are also a few Alliance Francaise documents in the scrapbook related to governance and Hyde's voting proxy.
- Series VI. Legion of Honor Letter Books, 1921, 1923, 1928; .83 Linear feet in two boxes of bound volumes
  7 bound volumes of cards and letters sent to Hyde upon his promotions within the French government's Legion of Honor (Légion d'honneur). Volumes 1 and 2 include letters from 1921 when Hyde was promoted to the rank of Commander (Commandeur). (He had first been elected to the Legion as a Chevalier in 1900.) Volumes 3 and 4 include letters from 1923 when Hyde was promoted to Grand Officer (Grand officier). Volumes 5-7 include letters from his promotion in 1928 to Grand Cross (Grand-croix). Volume 5 includes a letter and artwork from artist Ferdinand Bac. Most letters are in French, a few in German.
  The volumes are in original order and binding. Within each set of volumes (1921, 1923, 1928), the letters are in alphabetical order by correspondent.
  Gift of James Hazen Hyde, April 24, 1957 (transmittal letter for donation is inside front cover of Volume 1).
  - Letter Books, Volumes 1-4, 1921, 1923 (Box 33)
  - Letter Books, Volumes 5-7, 1928 (Box 34)